Pante, is there a way to speed up my
practice? Um,
well, the problem is that question
assumes you already know what the practice is.
you already know what the practice is.
So, you're going to try to speed
something up that you kind of already
know what it's about. Whereas, the more
important question is, do I know what
the practice is so that I can speed it
up? So So
cuz see
you can read the sutas you can even like
uh rationalize about what the obstacles
of your practice are but an obstacle is
an obstac is defined as an obstacle by
knowing what the goal is.
So as you don't know what the goal is
how can you know what the obstacles are
so that you can then remove them and
then speed up the practice.
So that's why for as long as you don't
have the right view yet, you shouldn't
assume like, okay, I'm already doing the
practice semi correctly. Uh, but it's
just not going fast enough, which is
what most people assume. Like
it's sort of already mostly going in the
right direction, but it's just it just
takes time. So I just need to kind of
dedicate more effort to it or something.
But more than nine times out of 10 uh again
more than nine times out of 10 uh again
well if you don't have the right view if
you're not a sabana your idea of the
practice is the problem your ideal of
the practice is the obstacle.
Um so
start trying to figure out what the
practice is abandoning wrong views.
And uh how do you do that? Well by
admitting first of all that your views
are not right.
because if you don't then you again you
might even read the sutas you might hear
uh stuff from the Buddha's own mouth but
as he himself said when somebody comes
with the the notion that they understand
what they don't understand
that is a categorical obstacle for them
to enter the path to the dharma to
skillful qualities because then when
they hear even the right thing they sort
of absorb it and and um sort of molded
into the thing that they already created
for themselves which again is is most
likely wrong. So then you can hear you
see it all the time like how people
would parrot the sutas
and and you know even before judging who
is right and who is wrong you see two
people holding completely different
views and quoting the same suta to
support their their points
which shows you that like yeah it's it's
if it if it if it were all about just
that information that you can just
transmit from one person to the other um
and then your view is right just based
on how you express it. Um then uh that
wouldn't happen like you'd have
everybody agreeing on the same things uh
even though just because the information
is the same but it's not even in that
case you can see how the information
lands differently based on the
assumptions that you have behind it.
So then yeah recognize
um because you know the the criteria for
knowing that you don't know what the
practice is uh is that you're still
subject to suffering. It's not that you
kind of externally haven't matched some
kind of idea or or or sort of threshold.
It's like that very immediate
recognition of in day-to-day life when
problems arise,
uh, I feel trapped and I still need to
do something. I still need to hope. I
still need to sort of, um, move
variables around and expect that
hopefully I won't suffer.
Um, so then unless that's not the case
anymore and you're free from doubt as to
how you can be free from suffering in
every situation regardless of what it
is, then you can't be trying to speed up
your practice cuz you still don't know
what the practice is. If you knew what
the practice was, you'll be free from
doubt that again in any situation you
know the way out and you wouldn't be
trapped anymore.
So then all those teachings that the
Buddha gave to you know like uh um the
sense of urgency and and don't be
negligent you know uh it was all based
on the right view as the foundation to
monks who had already been they were
clear about what they had to do they
were just not doing it as diligently as
they should.
So then to ask the question in a
different way, are there any factors
that support
the questioning of one's views that
accelerate? >> Yeah. Well, see, everybody has kind of
>> Yeah. Well, see, everybody has kind of
like
situations where they know that they
suffer basic or or they know that they're still
basic or or they know that they're still
subject to craving to defilements,
but they kind of um explain it away. one
way or the other is like not being
relevant. It's like some something that sort of
It's like some something that sort of
it's it's it will sort itself out or
it's not a big deal or it's just how it
is. It's just my personality or
something. Uh but if you start
uncovering those things and you start
realizing just basically the extent of
your non-development
um that gives you the sense of like okay
so it can't possibly be right whatever I
think the practice is however right it
feels cuz see uh anything shorter than
that than that sort of direct u
measurement could still be wrong cuz you could you
could still be wrong cuz you could you
know even even rely on external u an
external reference point like which is
what the what this what's it called um
Kalamasuta describes like this aesthetic
is my teacher
um he he agrees that I do understand the
teaching that he teaches
and then what if he's wrong what if he
doesn't what if he does understand it
but he doesn't see how you don't
understand it and then he would tell you
yes you do understand the teaching. So
basically anything except this direct
comparison of your own ability to
overcome suffering
uh is still going to be uh uh able to
mislead you and not show you just how
much work you still need to do. And
that's basically all of what you see in
in in modern traditions and stuff. It's
like all these uh um goalposts that are
externally defined as in like okay you
get this experience and then you get the
next experience and then when you enter
this samati that has this characteristic
it means you're at this and this stage.
Um and precisely that's why you can have
so many people who like complete all
those uh stages backwards and forwards
and then uh you find out that they
whatever have been breaking basic
precepts for years.
Um, and see if they hadn't dismissed
those tendencies that they would have
seen in themselves if they were honest
like how their mind was still pressuring
them towards this or that thing and they
had dug deeper into those things. They
would have realized like yes, I can't
possibly claim that I know the way out
of craving because look at what's
happening to my own mind. But when you
don't see it as important,
uh you can pretty much make it like
completely disappear from your point of
view if you exercise that cover up long
enough. So in fact, the Buddha said it the the
So in fact, the Buddha said it the the
basis for faith
which you could pretty much say is
basically that sense of urgency, that
sense of like there is this this resolve
that you get when you realize there's
something I need to develop. Uh the
basis for that is suffering.
It's not like like an external
inspiration. It's suffering. Recognizing
how you personally are still suffering
in ways that you know again would be
obvious if you just look for them. It's
not that it's like concealed or
something. It's just you you're used to
to to just covering it up and and and
making it seem unimportant when actually
the arrow of suffering is very much
touching you.
So then um things like precepts, non-distraction,
non-distraction,
spending time in seclusion, those could
be all things that you can do without
the right view that would help you to
reduce the coverups that you would
usually >> Well, yeah. But let's say for most
>> Well, yeah. But let's say for most
people,
>> for the average lay person,
>> um but if th those things were actually
enough in themselves, then you wouldn't
have so many cases of monks who have
been practicing for decades and and
clearly still have wrong views. Um
because again it's like you can get used
to that environment to to those
circumstances very much where like like
genuinely you wouldn't want to disrobe
let's say um but if you you could for
example cover up your own
um dependence on your tradition as a as
something that like if you were to if if
you were placed in a completely
different environment where people
didn't agree with the values that you
have um and and there wasn't that kind
of external reinforcement to tell you
that what you're doing is right, you
would fall apart.
Uh that's just one example. It's not
that you know it's cuz again it varies
depends on the person like for somebody
they may um not care about breaking the
precepts and not care about tradition.
Other for another person they don't care
about breaking the precepts they do care
about tradition. The other person uh do
cares about the precepts but not about
tradition. So it's like
what is the thing that for you
personally if you if you if you reflect
honestly like this sort of uh hits me at
the core
and then it's probably not going to be
just one thing. Uh but it's kind of like
you start uncovering basically all these
you'll find it you start finding it left
and right eventually but it's just like
again you were so used to just
explaining it away even sometimes with
things in the sutas like imagine
somebody who who reads the sutras and
says oh an arant still experiences uh uh
pleasant and unpleasant feelings and
then they justify all sorts of like
again even breaking precepts and stuff
that like oh no it's because still has
uh these these kind of they still
experience feelings. So you know all
this is justified. So it can go
extremely far in in how you can again
cover these things up and you would see
it at like all these supposed lays that
exist and so on
means like they completely don't accept
at all acknowledge at all all the
defilements that they still have because
it doesn't feel like a defilement when
you act out of it when all when all the
when you're used to acting out of it
when all the circumstances around it
allow you to act out of it and you can
just sort of like uh get over it quickly
whenever it comes up.
>> So it boils down to self honesty.
>> Yeah.
>> Asking yourself the right questions.
>> Yeah. I mean even the Buddha like he
wouldn't have become the Buddha had he
not realized wait yes I had developed
all this lofty stuff but can I still
suffer? And then he realized yes. Uh,
and most people would read that and sort
of think like, "Oh, yeah, of course."
But, um, like again, most of the time
with way less development than that,
you're already covering things up and
not acknowledging how you're actually
still suffering.
So, that's why actually, again, um, I
think that's another thing that's
overlooked. The first noble truth is
suffering. It's not like uh oh we already have that
It's not like uh oh we already have that
that understood like we're already
suffering we know what that is and then
now it's just about uh discovering the
sensation and so on. It's like you you
don't even recognize your own suffering.
You're used to covering it up.
So then how can you be practicing and
speeding up the practice of overcoming
something that you don't clearly see?
So what would then be the difference
between unpleasant feeling and actual
suffering? >> Well, it's what I said before. Like does
>> Well, it's what I said before. Like does
it hit you to the core? Like do you feel
immediately that you already need to do
something? Is there an action that if if if you
Is there an action that if if if you
weren't able to do it, you would just be
boiling in this discomfort?
So that's the arrow that the Buddha
talks about that it kind of hits you to
the heart
and you can see throughout your day that
you experience unpleasant things.
Everybody necessarily experiences
unpleasant things that don't actually
hit them in that way that don't actually
cause them to
enter the state of compulsion of having
to do something.
It's just an unpleasant feeling and you
you don't have much of an issue
withstanding it. But then there are
other things that like if you were to
um again if you were to to reflect
honestly you would see like as soon as
this arises you would see your mind
immediately already leaning towards some
sort of response
and that's where where the suffering is.
So that's why it goes um hand in hand
with with action. Kama as as the Buddha
called it like the the the impulse
towards action
is another way of describing what what
you abandon when you develop your mind.
It's that immediate sort of like whether
you do it or not is just an impulse
there to respond to this.
And again, precepts and stuff like for
most people that's that's
that's going to already reveal it, but
you can have plenty of of situations
where your your impulse to respond isn't
on the level of breaking the precepts
for whatever reason.
Uh you need to say something. And even
if it's like a again it's not a
um like impolite harsh speech and and
sort of this clear violation.
It might even be the most polite thing
and and might seem good to everybody
else but you need to do it. And that's
the problem
because even if you succeed in doing it,
the fact that you had to do it, that's
already suffering.
Like even if you are able to do it every
single time the impulse comes up, merely
having the impulse and being pressured
into it, it's already suffering. Like
just imagine even if somebody forces you
to do something and there you you're
perfectly able to to to go ahead with
that uh demand
and nobody punishes you or anything. But
the fact that you were forced that's in
itself suffering.
So suffering in that sense would then be
the inability
to stay or to not act out of unpleasant
feeling. Yes. But
Yes. But
you have to keep in mind that you you
basically like you'll catch yourself
already. You you catch yourself already within
You you catch yourself already within
suffering.
So, it's not like you're going to see
the unpleasant feeling and then you're
going to see, oh, I have the impulse to
act and then like, no, no. You're going
to realize that you already are caught
up in the impulse to to get rid of some
unpleasant feeling.
Because if if you were aware of the
impulse and it were a matter of like,
okay, I'm going to follow it or not,
that that wouldn't be that wouldn't
really be an impulse.
That that's the whole point of the mind.
And that's why it's compared to an
animal. It's like it's it's doing stuff
even without you telling it
and then you can sort of afterwards try
to contain it and stuff but like it has
its own impulses that come first.
If one finds oneself pressured by an
unpleasant feeling,
one recognizes this impulse wanting to
get rid of that unpleasant feeling.
Um but sometimes it happens as well that
one despite recognizing the impulse one
still acts out of it.
>> Why is that the case? Well, yeah, but
you wouldn't be able to act out of it if
you recognized it.
So that's that's what you have to see
ties into to the whole thing I was
describing before like even your notion
of what recognizing the impulse means
might not be correct because otherwise
you wouldn't have acted out of it.
So in fact that's why in the sutras um
the Buddha describes the um satipatana
of the mind
not as like uh when a viku has a lustful
mind he he he changes the lustful mind
for a different mind says he maintains
maintains perspective over the lustful
mind and that's it and based on this
practice uh he abides independent not taking up
uh he abides independent not taking up
anything in the world. So in other
words, if you actually recognize an
impulse as it is the impulse of the
chitta, uh that's it. Like not only will you be
uh that's it. Like not only will you be
able incapable of acting out of it, uh
that mere recognition is already
training the mind and making that
impulse subside cuz it's like trapped.
So even if it's still there, there is no
expression of it. So it it has to run
out of fuel.
Um but that's actually like see when
when you
let's say uh uh uh any desire comes up
in your mind and then you have this
phase where like you sort of battling
with yourself about it doubting should I
do it should I not do it and then as
soon as you go with it the question
disappears
and it's like well of course you can it
can come back and stuff but it will
never be there and it will never be be
magnified to the same extent as if you
were to stop again and reconsider like
should I do this, should I not do it. So
the the the fact that you're in it
already means you can't consider it with
the same amount of perspective. That's
why having that right level of
perspective prevents you from getting
into it in the first place. Getting into
it even with your uh uh welcoming let
alone actions of body and speech.
So of course like um if you catch
yourself acting out of something
um it doesn't mean like okay so because
I can't see the impulse whatever I'll
just keep uh uh acting out verbally and
physically uh sorry yeah verbally and
physically and then later I'll do
something else to discern the impulse.
It's like no you have to stop doing the
things that prevent you from recognizing
the impulse as it is. And that's what
the precepts are for. So, it's like it's
not showing you the impulse or or um
clarifying the perspective of what the
impulse actually is. It's just uh
stopping you from doing the the things
that definitely cover it up.
Um and uh and then well, the rest is for
you to clarify that view to again
recognize your own experience of
suffering as it arises. Recognizing what
is the suffer uh what is the unpleasant
feeling and what is that kind of
compulsion to to respond to it
and that is only going to happen if you
want to recognize that difference. If
you are trying to make the effort cuz
anybody could just keep precepts for any
random reason and they're not making
that effort. They're not going to
discern that difference and they're not
going to understand suffering.
But would you then say that it's a
matter of not recognizing it as an
impulse at all or not being able to
maintain the perspective of it's an
impulse because you drop, as you said,
you drop it at one point because you
can't just uh withstand the
>> Yeah. Well, see, you can recognize it as
an impulse.
>> Uh and you might even constantly
recognize it as an impulse. uh but there
is a difference in the quality or type
of that recognition.
Uh so for example you see even in these
like meditation techniques how they
would describe that people would quote
unquote see their mental states arising
and ceasing and stuff and even if it
let's say it actually was because there
has to be some link. It's not like
you're talking about greed arose and
there was genuinely nothing. Uh the
problem is
you're seeing it with that kind of
overly focused direct attention which means
which means
even if that is an impulse
the root impulse which is the one that
matters it remains completely unseen
such as why am I observing this?
Why am I trying to get something out of
this? So see even the restlessness to
figure out what the uh what the
suffering is
uh if you that is the actual impulse.
So see in in that scenario like that's
the root of the experience. So then
somebody could be uh uh thinking okay
let me figure out what suffering is let
me let me look closer at these things
that are happening in my mind and then
they see the greed coming up and they
see the aversion coming up and the
restlessness coming up but they don't
see how that whole endeavor is
underllayed by a mind of lessness that's
pressuring me to do this observation.
Not that it's inherently so, but at that
time that was the pressure that was
driving your experience and you didn't
see it as such.
So that's the need for yonisara that
described and and that's why it's a
condition for the right view as well. Uh
cuz anybody can talk about greed and
stuff but you see um it's not just
the the the the random things that you
can point to in your experience. It's
what is the root of it right now? What
is the thing that it converges on?
The thing where you're actually, let's
say, most emotionally engaged because
you can have a thought of greed that
just comes up. But precisely, you're
seeing it you're you're seeing it come
up like you're not engaging with it.
It's not an issue. But what you are
engaged with is that restlessness of let
me observe this. And precisely the stuff
that you don't see is the stuff that
hinders you. the stuff that captivates
your perspective.
So that's why it's so important to
always be uh um reclarifying like that
intention behind your actions even on
the mental level like why am I watching
my mind right now and then you would see
oh my mind is actually in a state of
restlessness that's associated with an
action of watching my mind and then you
realize in order to see my mind I would
have to stop watching it and then I
would be seeing it on the right level.
So how would you then speed up the
practice when you have the right view?
>> Yeah. Well, it wouldn't be a different
principle. It's like if you had the
right view, it just means you have the
criteria to recognize what's an
obstruction now. So it would be exactly
the same thing as in like
you would be uncovering the things that
you are
excusing yourself in like the little
forms of creative aversion and delusion
that you're ex excusing yourself in
regard to.
Uh and the only difference is now like
you wouldn't have to doubt your criteria
for what is greed aversion and delusion
because having that criteria is what the
right view is.
Um and and your practice would be
obstructed for exactly the same reason
because you're acting out of stuff,
not including it. Uh um making up
whatever excuses you could come up with,
it doesn't matter. The point is the mind
is receiving the feel that it needs for
these states to continue, for these
pressures to continue.
Um so
it would never be like oh you you kind
of um commit to some special kind of
practice uh like go on a special retreat and
uh like go on a special retreat and
stuff that will uh speed things up and
bring them closer to the surface. The
thing is like
if you did that
it would be as a as a way of you not
acting out of your mental states of your
wholesome mental states because that's
the problem like when people look for
these sort of ways to speed up a
practice the the the
view that floats behind that is like
there are these things that you can do
which are wholesome in themselves
regardless of why I'm doing them.
And somebody who has a right view would
not be able to think that because they
would have understood it's exactly the
intention that determines the quality of
the action regardless of what it is.
So then they wouldn't be able to commit
to like oh I'll spend 3 months even
doing exactly to the letter everything
that the Buddha said because they would
know that even that they can do wrong
with restlessness with greed with all
these mental states and they would
instead put first
uh seeing the state of my mind seeing
whether I'm acting out of it if it's unh
wholesome and then everything else is secondary to
So it's like that's why the the practice
would be kind of hindered by you or or
or uh uh slowed down by you.
Uh not because like you couldn't have
the perfect circumstances that would
have allowed you to commit to this
method hard enough.
It's like you could have circumstances
that are
making it more likely for you to make
wrong choices as in prioritize dealing
with external things compared to to
restraining your mind. Like if you're
let's say in an overly busy environment
and then like because of your own lack
of training then you you sort of makes
it easier for you to to distract
yourself with things that are going on
externally. But even then it's it's
because of the choices that you're
making.
So even when the sutas speak about the
the things or the yeah the things that
hinder the progression of somebody with
the right view of someone in training.
>> Yeah.
>> It's their delight in work, their
delight in sleep,
>> their delight in company.
>> It's not like oh because they happen to
be in in such and such environment. No,
it's because they are delighting in
these things. They're pursuing them that
hinders their progress. Why? Cuz it
automatically means they're putting
first something whatever it is external
over that crucial question of why am I
doing it because they would see that
they're doing it out of the light and
that it cannot possibly be wholesome. M
so if people take up those things as an
external practice like okay the less I
sleep the better the less I'm with
people the better the more I'm in
seclusion the better but you do you
understand what the light is
>> and
that's basically like
many people would start out with this
assumption like
pretty much it it automatically carries
the light like I don't need to question
it it just automatically carries the
light and even if Let's say you fac fact
and even if Let's say you fac fact
factorally stopped the lighting and
sleep as a result of that practice and
you overcame the need for sleep. Uh
you're not any closer to actually
developing the right view which means
you will lose that eventually and not
just that but you are acting out of
other stuff that you don't see even if
you overcame this one thing.
So that's why yeah you can do whatever
practices to and then factually you
could hear study stories of people who
their lust diminished or whatever the
anger diminished or whatever but what's
the full picture there like what about
everything else? Are they more sensitive
to uh people disagreeing with them for
example? Are they most more sensitive to
having an environment that they don't
like? And then you would see inevitably
one of those things will have to be
there if they don't have the if they
don't have the right view because when
you don't see craving you have to be
acting out of it in some form. You can't
be pure accidentally.
How would one then remove the delight
out of those very things that you
mentioned? Uh well, first you have to
understand what the light is.
So
um you could take the same thread that I
described before. It's not even like
that the action is pleasant.
Um because some things are going to be
pleasant and you can't possibly prevent
that. Like even if you go out of your
way to prevent it, it's not possible.
Um, so
when something is pleasant, is there an
impulse to us more of it?
Regardless of what it is,
because of course you could say, "Yo,
yeah, I don't care about food. I don't
care about sexuality. I don't care about
entertainment." But is there something
for you that is pleasant that when it
arises, you have this basically like if
I go if I don't go for more of it, my
mind is kind of eating itself.
So that's the delight
and then that's what you would need to
guard yourself against. Even if it's not
there now that doesn't mean you just cuz
even the sutas say that same one I
described it says when your mind is is
not affected with greed not affected
with aversion not affected with delusion
you still have to know that you still
have to keep perspective in regard to
that because otherwise it's like oh I'll
just leave the bank because there there
are no thieves here so I don't need to
guard the the door anymore
and then yeah you will start to see
again it It's always like you catch
yourself having already fallen into into the
having already fallen into into the
light. It's not like you sort of see the
thing coming cuz if it if that were
possible, you would never fall into it
in the first place. So it's like you
catch yourself already delighting in
something. You catch your mind already
having this momentum and then you
realize well first of all you if you
have that perspective developed you see
that the light arisen that's the
practice of somebody with the right view
and then that automatically kind of
corrects the picture and by absolute
extension they won't be able to keep
acting out externally.
But initially like okay let's say it's
it's not 100% clear what the light is
but you can see these actions that like
even with reasoning you could say that's
almost 90% chance not wholesome
then okay well you stop it and you try
to keeping in mind still like I still
need to understand what the light is you
don't feel justified in like okay now I
just every time this direction comes up
for me I just deny it cuz then that's
still carrying an assumption that that
basically it's not doing justice to how
much you still don't know.
Which means like sometimes you could
deny something that wasn't actually unh
wholesome and that's bad. It's not safer
because it keeps reinforcing the wrong
criteria. >> Denying something that's not unh
>> Denying something that's not unh
wholesome.
>> So it keeps keeps kind of feeding that
wrong emphasis that you have.
So there isn't really a method in that
sense to when you don't see these things
for yourself.
It's like if you keep in mind that you
don't see it for yourself and you keep
the motivation and and the and the sense
of
um
of perspective of why it matters that
you don't see it for yourself. Cuz you
know random drunkard in in the middle of
a village could say I don't care. I
don't understand the Buddhist teaching
because he doesn't understand why that's
relevant. So, you have to be careful that it
So, you have to be careful that it
doesn't become like um
oh yeah, I recognize I I still don't
have the right view and stuff, but it's
it's kind of like this this externally
projected ideal that because I'm a
Buddhist, I should have the right view
and this is good. And that's you see
that all the time in people like they
would recognize that they have the right
view, but it would almost be like
completely fine with that. Um it's not a
big deal.
It means you don't recognize the level
of problems that this creates for you.